Guide to the Views of the Pacific Northwest
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Views of the Pacific Northwest.
1828-1860
1854-1860
WA MSS S-1817
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7
(6 boxes)
Photographic prints, drawings, and watercolors chiefly depicting sights on the Northwest Coast, particularly around Vancouver Island. The images were originally housed in a scrapbook kept by an unidentified individual; based on the contents of the scrapbook it is presumed that the person was a member of the joint U.S./British Northwest Boundary Commission. The photographs, taken by an unidentified photographer or photographers, depict deck scenes from what may be the H.M.S. Satellite; Victoria Indians; Hudson's Bay Company outposts at Fort Vancouver, San Juan Island, and Victoria; encampments on San Juan Island; Nanaimo and Esquimalt, Vancouver Island; Valparaiso, Chile; and Stanley Harbor in the Falkland Islands. The drawings (in both pen and ink as well as pencil) and watercolors, include four works signed by James Madison Alden, as well as drawings by W. H. Hall, J. Palmer, James Robertson, Marcus Lowther, B. Tucker, and possibly William McMurtrie. Subjects include Vancouver Island; San Juan Island; Pt. Grenville, Washington Territory; the Fraser River; coastal landmarks of South America; Victoria Indians, encampments, ships, and birds.
Northwest Boundary Commission ($d (1857-1862))
Alden, James Madison, 1834-1922
Hall, W. H., fl. ca. 1850-1860
Lowther, Marcus
McMurtrie, W. B. (William Birch)
Palmer, J., fl. ca. 1850-1860
Robertson, James, fl. ca. 1850-1860
Tucker, B., fl. ca. 1850-1860
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Unspecified. Consult curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
HISTORICAL NOTE
In 1846, Britain and the United States agreed by treaty to draw the western Canadian-American border along the 49th parallel. A joint American-British commission was established, and in 1857 the Americans sent the first field team to the Pacific Northwest. Archibald Campbell served as the American commissioner, William McMurtrie was the official artist on board the U.S.S. Steamer Active, and James Madison Alden was an artist, also on board the U.S.S. Steamer Active. In the summer of 1858 the British team arrived, composed of army personnel, primarily from the Royal Engineers. The British team brought photographic equipment with them and at least two members of the team made photographs.
Scope and Contents
Views of the Pacific Northwest consists of photographic prints, drawings, and watercolors chiefly depicting sights on the Northwest Coast, particularly around Vancouver Island (a few European and South American scenes and landmarks also are included). The images originally were housed in a scrapbook kept by an unidentified individual; based on the contents of the scrapbook it is presumed that the person was a member of the joint U.S./British Northwest Boundary Commission.
By the time the scrapbook arrived at Yale its condition had seriously deteriorated. Consequently, the volume was disassembled by conservators, and the views were matted and housed in portfolios according to size. Manuscript notes and captions, which appear on the verso of some of the pieces, were photocopied and the copies mounted on the back of the mats. Items found lying loose within the scrapbook were designated "Miscellany" and numbered; they are listed in the finding aid at the end of Part II. The volume itself, which still contains some manuscript captions, was retained; it is housed in box 6.
The photographs, taken by an unidentified photographer or photographers, depict deck scenes from a ship that may be the H.M.S. Satellite; Victoria Indians; Hudson's Bay Company outposts at Fort Vancouver, San Juan Island, and Victoria; encampments on San Juan Island; Nanaimo and Esquimalt, Vancouver Island; Valparaiso, Chile; and Stanley Harbor in the Falkland Islands.
The drawings (in both pen and ink as well as pencil) and watercolors, include four works signed by James Madison Alden, as well as drawings by W. H. Hall, J. Palmer, James Robertson, Marcus Lowther, B. Tucker, and possibly William McMurtrie. Scenes depicted include Vancouver Island; San Juan Island; Pt. Grenville, Washington Territory; the Fraser River; coastal landmarks of South America; Victoria Indians, encampments, ships, and birds.
This finding aid lists the contents of the former scrapbook three different ways: according to format (Part I), according to their original order in the scrapbook (Part II), and according to the present storage order of the materials (Part III). The lists for Part I and Part II provide references to the current box and folder location of the materials.
Coasts -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- British Columbia -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Northwest, Pacific -- Pictorial works; Voyages to the Pacific coast; British Columbia -- Pictorial works; Canada -- Boundaries -- United States; Esquimalt (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Fort Vancouver (Wash.) -- Pictorial works; Fraser River (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Nanaimo (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Northwest boundary of the United States; Northwest Coast of North America -- Pictorial works; Northwest, Pacific -- Pictorial works; Northwest, Pacific -- Description and travel; San Juan Island (Wash.) -- Pictorial works; Stanley (Falkland Islands) -- Pictorial works; United States -- Boundaries -- Canada; Valparaíso (Chile) -- Pictorial works; Vancouver Island (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Victoria (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Drawings (visual works); Panoramas; Panoramic photographs; Photographic prints; Watercolors (paintings); Hudson's Bay Company -- Pictorial works; Northwest Boundary Commission ($d (1857-1862)); Satellite (Ship)
- Part I. Material by format
  Scope and Contents
  Part I is arranged into four sections: Photographs, Drawings, Watercolors, and Miscellaneous. The Photographs are listed chronologically; undated photographs are listed at the end. Drawings and watercolors are arranged alphabetically by artist. Unidentified works are listed at the end of each category. The box and folder numbers refer to the present location of the items.
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - "Stanley Harbour, Falkland Island. H.M.S. Satellite at anchor." Photographic print, 10.6 x 15.8 cm., [1857 Feb] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Town of Stanley, Falkland Islands." Photographic print, 14.2 x 20.9 cm., [1857 Jul] (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "The American N.W. Boundary Camp, 49th Parallel, Semiahmoo, Gulf of Georgia. The British Possessions." Photographic print, 10.8 x 19.6 cm., [1857 Aug] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Camp of the American Northwest Boundary Commission, Semiahmoo." Photographic print, 22.2 x 29.4 cm., [1857 Aug] (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - "Hudson's Bay Co. Fort, Victoria, Vancouver Island." Photographic print, 9.5 x 12.3 cm., [1857] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [Johnson, J.?] "1st encampment of U.S. Land Boundary Commission, Esquimalt, V.I." Photographic print, 15.7 x 21.6 cm. on mount 20.7 x 27.5 cm., [1858 Jul] (Box 5, Folder 54)
      J. Johnson is written in ink at bottom of print
    - "Buildings of the H[udson] B[ay] Co. establishment, San Juan Island." Two photographic prints joined together to form a panorama, 11.1 x 35.7 cm., [1859 Sep] (Box 6, Folder 67)
      Accompanied by holograph notes about the photograph
    - "Part of the U.S. Camp, San Juan Island." Photographic print, 17.4 x 21.9 cm., [1859 Nov 4] (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - "Encampment of Royal Marines. North end of San Juan, 13 miles from U.S. detachment. Landed from H.M.S. Satellite." Photographic print, 15.7 x 18.7 cm., [1860 Mar] (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Nanaimo. Gulf of Georgia, V.I. H.M.S. Satellite." Photographic print, 9.6 x 18.6 cm., [1860 Jun] (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - [H.M.S. Satellite?] deck, with officer sitting on cannon, four other sailors in view. Photographic print, 17.3 x 21.6 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - [H.M.S. Satellite?] deck, four men standing in the foreground. Photographic print, 19 x 22.1 cm. (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - [H.M.S. Satellite?] deck, two men seated, two men standing. Photographic print, 19.4 x 22.1 cm. (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - "Hudson's Bay Co. Fort Vancouver." Photographic print, 17.8 x 27.2 cm. on mount 27.2 x 34.6 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - "Angus McDonald. Factor, Hudson Bay Co." Photographic print, 20.1 x 11.9 cm. on mount 34.5 x 27.3 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - "Boundary, Mooyie River." Photographic print, 26.2 x 23.2 cm. on mount 34.6 x 27.3 cm (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - "Valparaiso." Photographic print, 16.3 x 20.9 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - [Valparaiso.] Photographic print, 16.1 x 21 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - [Valparaiso?] Photographic print, 9.6 x 20.8 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - [Valparaiso?] Photographic print, 15.4 x 21.3 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "A group of Victoria Indians taken on board H.M.S. Satellite" Photographic print, 10.5 x 14.6 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Victoria Indians: woman, man, and child. Photographic print, 8.3 x 10.6 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Rose Bank, Dun's hook, Esquimalt, Vancouver Island. The residence of W. A. G. Young, Esq." Photographic print, 11.6 x 15.9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Fenced in commons [?] with well and harbor in the background with ship at anchor. Photographic print, 17 x 21.5 cm. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - One story house with picket fence and two men in front. Photographic print, 22.5 x 28 cm. (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Two story house. Photographic print, 15.4 x 20 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Two story house with tree in front and woman at far left. Photographic print, 17.9 x 21.7 cm. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "Beverley. 3473 Nave W." [Interior of church.] Photographic print, 15.9 x 10.0 cm., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Painting of [Moses smiting the rock of Horeb, and making water come out of it?] Photographic print, 12.8 x 26.8 cm. (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Large square building with arch entrance in Europe or Asia. Photographic print, 19.9 x 25.9 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Two-story house (same as in Miscellany 2 and 3) with carriage, horses, and five people. Photographic print, 20.7 x 26.7 cm. (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - DRAWINGS
    - Alden, J. M. "Harbor -- San Juan Island. Disputed Territory. J. M. Alden, U.S.S. Steamer 'Active.'" Pen and ink and gray wash drawing, 23.6 x 30.6 cm., 1859 Sep (Box 4, Folder 41)
      Accompanied by holograph description of San Juan Island
    - Alden, J. M. "View on Nanaimo River, Vancouver Island." Pen and ink and gray wash drawing, 24.2 x 32.6 cm., 1858 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Hall, W. H. Points and other landmarks. Four pen and ink drawings, 11.2 x 26.8 cm. (Box 4, Folder 45)
      "By W. H. Hall, Mid. H.M.S. Satellite."
    - Hall, W. H. "Western Coast, Vancouver Isla. by W. H. Hall, Mid. H.M.S. Satellite." pen and ink drawing, 5.9 x 14.1 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lowther, Marcus. "[Chinchas?] The Defiance of N.Y. loading." Pen and ink drawing, 11.1 x 15.0 cm., 1854 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "Cornish Bar (looking up) Fraser R[iver]." Pencil drawing, 13.3 x 18.0 cm., 1859 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "Fort Yale (looking up)" Pencil drawing, 13.6 x 20.3 cm., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "From Emery [bank?] (down) the Fraser." Pencil drawing, 13.1 x 17.8 cm., n.y. Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "R[iver] Fraser, "Enterprise" frozen in below point." Pencil drawing, 15.4 x 17.5 cm., 1859 Jan 10 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "Redscaur R[iver]." Pencil drawing, 10.3 x 12.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] Three-masted side-wheeler. Pencil drawing, 17.6 x 26.3 cm., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "(Up the) Fraser, Mouth of the Quiquealla R[iver]." Pencil drawing, 13.8 x 20.8 cm. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Palmer, J. "Vancouver Island." pen and ink drawing of camp, 11.4 x 18.3 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Robertson, James. "Entrance to Albirni canal (Barclay Sound)," "Hills to the Right of Canal (Barclay Sn.)," "Entrance to San Juan Harbr. (Juan-de-Fuca Strait)." Pen and ink drawing, 18.6 x 22.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 43)
      "Sketched by Jas. Robertson, M.A., H.M.S. Satellite."
    - Robertson, James. "Entrance to Barclay Sound," "Inlet at the Head of Eu-clu-li-at Harb. from anchorage," "Swiss Boy Bay from anchorage." Pen and ink sketch, 18.6 x 23.4 cm. (Box 4, Folder 44)
      "Sketched by Jas. Robertson, Masters Assist." With annotations in later hand, "Barclay Sound, Vancouver Isl." and "Western Coast, Vancouver Island."
    - Robertson, James. "Southern Part of the Head of the Albirni canal. Western Coast, Vancouver Island. Sketched by Jas. Robertson, Masters Assist." Pen and ink drawing, 13.3 x 18.0 cm. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Tucker, B. "The famous monastery of Megaspeleon...in ancient Achaia...." Pen and ink drawing, 13.2 x 19.3 cm., 1839 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Court House, Devon. South View of Court House." Pencil drawing with drawing of man playing [a piano?] on verso: "Mr. [Brownell?]. F. Mores [?] for R.N. School August 12, 1842," 12.0 x 17.4 cm., 1842, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "From Lee hill, Devonshire." Pen and ink drawing, 16.5 x 24.4 cm., n.y. Jan 29 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "1st night's encampment in British Columbia." Pen and ink and gray wash drawing, 12.4 x 17.6 cm., 1859 Jul 4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Accompanied by holograph notes on the first night's encampment in British Columbia
    - "Indian canoe & natives." pen and ink drawing, 9.3 x 17.4 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "The [stormy?] Petrel -- which surrounded the Satellite on the passage from Valparaiso to Calif." Pen and ink and gray wash drawing, 17.6 x 13.0 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Two masted ship with note "Drawn from memory by a Songa [Songhee?] Indian (N W Coast of America) to the Northd. of Fort Simpson...." Pencil drawing, 16.3 x 14.2 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Note possibly written by William McMurtrie
  - WATERCOLORS
    - Alden, J. M. "At Pt. Grenville, W.T." Watercolor, 17.1 x 26.8 cm. on paper 24.4 x 33.9 cm., 1854 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Alden, J.M. Fort Vancouver, Oregon. Watercolor, 23.6 x 30.7 cm., [1854] (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - "No. 2. The same as No. 1 only a different view. H.M.S. Satellite." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 16.0 x 11.9 cm., [1857] Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "The little bird which flew on the Satellite's [Port?] and was caught as in a cage when the [Port?] was lowered." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 8.5 x 19.0 cm., 1857 Apr 18 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      "Lat 14 S Long 18 W."
    - "Euclueliat Village, Barclay Sound, Vancouver Island, N.W. Coast. H.M.S. Satellite." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 24 x 36 cm., 1859 Mar (Box 6, Folder 71)
      Accompanied by holograph caption
    - "[Songhee?] Village. North West Coast Vancouver Island. Barclay Sound. H.M.S. Satellite." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 27.3 x 43 cm., 1859 Mar (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - [H.M.S. Satellite, Head of the Albirni Canal, North West Coast of Vancouver Island, Barclay Sound.] Pen and ink and watercolor, 26.4 x 42.7 cm., [1859 Mar 9] (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - "Camp at San Juan Island." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 19.8 x 34.6 cm., 1859 Jul 27 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      Accompanied by holograph notes on the camp at San Juan Island
    - British encampment. Watercolor, 17.1 x 47.9 cm., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Coastal landmarks, C. Frio and Rio de Janeiro. Pen and ink and watercolor drawings, 22.7 x 28.6 cm. (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Coastal landmarks, Tierra del Fuego, Cape St. Vincent, Magdalena Island. Pen and ink and watercolor drawings, 22.7 x 28.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Coastal landmarks, Capa Froward, Cape Providence, Cape Pillar. Pen and ink and watercolor drawings, 22.7 x 28.5 cm. (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Coastal landmarks, East Falkland and Patagonian Mission House, Rappel Island. Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 21.7 x 27.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Drawing of microorganisms "Found in phosphorescent seawater, magnified 120 diameters." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 12.6 x 17.9 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Four indians, three of them seated, one standing. Pencil, pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 25.5 x 19.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Three one story houses with front porches, with three men in front, and one man in doorway of center house. Watercolor, 25.2 x 34.2 cm. (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - MISCELLANEOUS
    - Original covers to scrapbook, with eight of the original leaves, four of them with holograph captions. 43.7 x 26.8 cm., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - "Thrakshkayiksh. Fort Simpson. Four months at school." Holograph, with note on side "Original. M.", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Ship at dock, published by J. Dickinson, 114 New Bond Street. Lithograph [?], 24.6 x 16.5 cm., 1828 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Part II. Original order of scrapbook
  Part II lists the order of the items in the scrapbook, before it was disbound. The headings list the page numbers where the items were originally mounted. The page numbers not listed represent blank pages in the scrapbook. The items at the end given miscellany numbers were found lying loose with the scrapbook. Box and folder numbers at left refer to the present storage location of the items.
  - Covers
    - Original covers to scrapbook, with eight of the original leaves, four of them with holograph captions. 43.7 x 26.8 cm., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Page 1
    - [H.M.S. Satellite?] deck, four men standing in the foreground. Photographic print, 19 x 22.1 cm. (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - [H.M.S. Satellite?] deck, two men seated, two men standing. Photographic print, 19.4 x 22.1 cm. (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Page 3
    - [H.M.S. Satellite?] deck, with officer sitting on cannon, four other sailors in view. Photographic print, 17.3 x 21.6 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Fenced in commons [?] with well and harbor in the background with ship at anchor. Photographic print, 17 x 21.5 cm. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Page 4
    - "Nanaimo. Gulf of Georgia, V.I. H.M.S. Satellite." Photographic print, 9.6 x 18.6 cm., [1860 Jun] (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Page 5
    - Three one story houses with front porches, with three men in front, and one man in doorway of center house. Watercolor, 25.2 x 34.2 cm. (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Page 6
    - "A group of Victoria Indians taken on board H.M.S. Satellite" Photographic print, 10.5 x 14.6 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Page 7
    - "Hudson's Bay Co. Fort Vancouver." Photographic print, 17.8 x 27.2 cm. on mount 27.2 x 34.6 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Page 9
    - One story house with picket fence and two men in front. Photographic print, 22.5 x 28 cm. (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Pages 11, 12
    - Alden, J. M. "At Pt. Grenville, W.T." Watercolor, 17.1 x 26.8 cm. on paper 24.4 x 33.9 cm., 1854 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Page 13
    - "Encampment of Royal Marines. North end of San Juan, 13 miles from U.S. detachment. Landed from H.M.S. Satellite." Photographic print, 15.7 x 18.7 cm., [1860 Mar] (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Page 15
    - "Angus McDonald. Factor, Hudson Bay Co." Photographic print, 20.1 x 11.9 cm. on mount 34.5 x 27.3 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Page 17
    - [Johnson, J.?] "1st encampment of U.S. Land Boundary Commission, Esquimalt, V.I." Photographic print, 15.7 x 21.6 on mount 20.7 x 27.5 cm., [1858 Jul] (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Page 19
    - Hall, W. H. "Western Coast, Vancouver Isla. by W. H. Hall, Mid. H.M.S. Satellite." pen and ink drawing, 5.9 x 14.1 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Palmer, J. "Vancouver Island." pen and ink drawing of camp, 11.4 x 18.3 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Indian canoe & natives." pen and ink drawing, 9.3 x 17.4 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Page 21
    - Alden, J. M. "Harbor -- San Juan Island. Disputed Territory. J. M. Alden, U.S.S. Steamer 'Active.'" Pen and ink and gray wash drawing, 23.6 x 30.6 cm., 1859 Sep (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Page 23
    - "Boundary, Mooyie River." Photographic print, 26.2 x 23.2 cm. on mount 34.6 x 27.3 cm (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Page 25
    - Victoria Indians: woman, man, and child. Photographic print, 8.3 x 10.6 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Four indians, three of them seated, one standing. Pencil, pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 25.5 x 19.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - "Thrakshkayiksh. Fort Simpson. Four months at school." Holograph, with note on side "Original. M.", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Page 27
    - Robertson, James. "Entrance to Albirni canal (Barclay Sound)," "Hills to the Right of Canal (Barclay Sn.)," "Entrance to San Juan Harbr. (Juan-de-Fuca Strait)." Pen and ink drawing, 18.6 x 22.2 cm. (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Robertson, James. "Entrance to Barclay Sound," "Inlet at the Head of Eu-clu-li-at Harb. from anchorage," "Swiss Boy Bay from anchorage." Pen and ink sketch, 18.6 x 23.4 cm. (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Page 29
    - Robertson, James. "Southern Part of the Head of the Albirni canal. Western Coast, Vancouver Island. Sketched by Jas. Robertson, Masters Assist." Pen and ink drawing, 13.3 x 18.0 cm. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Hall, W. H. Points and other landmarks. Four pen and ink drawings, 11.2 x 26.8 cm. (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Page 31
    - "Rose Bank, Dun's hook, Esquimalt, Vancouver Island. The residence of W. A. G. Young, Esq." Photographic print, 11.6 x 15.9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Hudson's Bay Co. Fort, Victoria, Vancouver Island." Photographic print, 9.5 x 12.3 cm., [1857] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The American N.W. Boundary Camp, 49th Parallel, Semiahmoo, Gulf of Georgia. The British Possessions." Photographic print, 10.8 x 19.6 cm., [1857 Aug] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Page 32
    - "Part of the U.S. Camp, San Juan Island." Photographic print, 17.4 x 21.9 cm., 1859 Nov 4 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Page 33
    - British encampment. Watercolor, 17.1 x 47.9 cm., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Page 35
    - "Camp of the American Northwest Boundary Commission, Semiahmoo." Photographic print, 22.2 x 29.4 cm., [1857 Aug] (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Page 39
    - "Buildings of the H[udson] B[ay] Co. establishment, San Juan Island." Two photographic prints joined together to form a panorama, 11.1 x 35.7 cm., [1859 Sep] (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Page 42
    - "Camp at San Juan Island." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 19.8 x 34.6 cm., 1859 Jul 27 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Page 43
    - Alden, J. M. "View on Nanaimo River, Vancouver Island." Pen and ink and gray wash drawing, 24.2 x 32.6 cm., 1858 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Page 45
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "R[iver] Fraser, "Enterprise" frozen in below point." Pencil drawing, 15.4 x 17.5 cm., 1859 Jan 10 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "Redscaur R[iver]." Pencil drawing, 10.3 x 12.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "Cornish Bar (looking up) Fraser R[iver]." Pencil drawing, 13.3 x 18.0 cm., 1859 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Page 47
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "Fort Yale (looking up)" Pencil drawing, 13.6 x 20.3 cm., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "(Up the) Fraser, Mouth of the Quiquealla R[iver]." Pencil drawing, 13.8 x 20.8 cm. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - [McMurtrie, William?] "From Emery [bank?] (down) the Fraser." Pencil drawing, 13.1 x 17.8 cm., n.y. Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Page 48
    - "1st night's encampment in British Columbia." Pen and ink and gray wash drawing, 12.4 x 17.6 cm., 1859 Jul 4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Page 49
    - "Euclueliat Village, Barclay Sound, Vancouver Island, N.W. Coast. H.M.S. Satellite." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 24 x 36 cm., 1859 Mar (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Page 51
      - "[Songhee?] Village. North West Coast Vancouver Island. Barclay Sound. H.M.S. Satellite." Pen and ink and watercolor drawing, 27.3 x 43 cm., 1859 Mar (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Page 53